And welcome back. And today we are going
to cover very very important topic in
Kafka, that is transaction handling.
Yes, in Kafka also, we can handle the
transaction. And very important
interview topic. And if you're working
with Kafka, then you might already know
how important to manage transaction in
Kafka.
Okay. So, let's just start without
wasting any time because it's a very big
topic and I have to cover a lot because
I don't want to skip any part of this.
Okay. So, let me tell you some quick
problems. Okay, which can happen without
transaction.
One problem I have already shared with
you during idempotency topic. Okay, in
Kafka
producer, we have discussed the
idempotency. This one. If you haven't
check it, check it out. Okay.
So, in that, I told you that
whenever the producer restart, it get a
new producer ID.
So, if you can recall
the idempotency video,
in that
the producer ID and sequence number,
these two are used
to maintain
ordering
and to avoid
duplicate.
Okay.
But, the problem is that this producer
ID is not stored anywhere at the broker
or coordinator side.
So, when the producer restart, it get a
new producer ID.
And when it get a new producer ID, so
there is a chance of duplicate. Okay.
If you have a doubt with this one,
kindly check it out this idempotency
internal video. You will get more
clarity on this one.
Okay.
So, that is the first problem.
The second problem is the partial right.
Let's see.
You are producing you have to produce
this two events. It should be atomic.
Means, if you are publishing order
event, then you should also publish
payment event. Okay, so these two has to
be happen together.
If you have scenario like this, then
without transaction, there is a
possibility of partial right.
Okay. Let's say that
order event success.
Payment event
success.
But, inventory event
failed.
Okay. So, my requirement was this three
should happen
together.
But, this two got success, but this got
failed.
Because of this, what happened is, let's
say, understand this. Order placed,
payment happened, but stocks
inventory is not reserved.
Okay. So, partial rights happen.
Inconsistent state happen in the system.
So, this is
also very important.
Okay. Whenever you have a condition
whether you have multiple events that
need to go together,
publish together.
If you all do not follow transaction,
this scenario can come. Partial rights
scenario.
Another is, so again, see, partial right
can happen from at the producer side.
And this idempotency one,
problem with idempotency, also we know
that it can happen at the producer side
only.
But, there is one more problem which can
happen at consumer side.
And that is like read, process, write
problem.
So,
let's say that the consumer
poll the event from the broker,
it got, hey, this is the offset. This is
the record, let's say.
And
so, this is first read. So, it read.
Then it process. Whatever the business
logic it has to do on this event, it do.
So, process.
Then write.
Then what it has happening is then it
publish another event based on this
processing, let's say. Okay. So, it's
business logic is that read the event,
process it, and publish another event.
In that scenario, there is a possibility
that
a duplicate
can happen. How? Let's say this
scenario. So, consumer read it,
processes it,
and write
to another event, another topic. Okay.
And now it has to commit the offset.
Hey, I am done with this
offset 50. But, what happened is this
offset got lost.
Okay. So, when the consumer did poll
again,
which offset it will get again? The same
50. Okay, it will send the same record
with offset 50.
Now, it will process it again
and it will publish it again.
Okay, so this duplicate processing
happening.
So, that can also be solved through
transaction.
Okay.
So, this three problems, understand
those three problems first properly.
Okay, then only proceed further.
So, the solution is transaction in
Kafka. Very very important topic from
interview perceptive. And even if you
are working it, then you must know
internal of it because
this is very critical and very
frequently used in the industry.
Okay. So, let's just start.
Step one is transaction ID.
Each producer assign themselves a unique
transaction ID.
Okay. If producer application has
multiple instances, then each instance
should have different unique ID. Very
important part.
Okay. And a question might have come to
your mind that why
each instance should have a different
transaction ID.
I will also explain that.
Unique ID should be stable. Means, if
application restart, this ID should not
be changed. So, what this three point is
that, let's say, you have a producer
application.
And if this application has multiple
instances, instance one, instance two,
instance three.
Okay, and this is the same producer
application, let's say. Same producer
application.
So, each instance should have unique
transaction ID. Transaction ID one,
transaction ID two, let's say,
transaction ID three. Unique transaction
ID.
So, question might have come to you that
why
for
my application is same, but only I have
different instances, why transaction ID
should be different for each instance
also?
It because
to avoid zombie fencing.
Don't worry about this. Okay, what is
zombie fencing and all because at this
point of time, it would be little early
for me to cover this.
As we proceed further, I will come to
this and things will automatically get
clear to you.
But, what I want is that at this point,
all we understand that each instance of
producer
should have a unique transaction ID.
And this transaction ID should be such
that even
if it restarted, this ID should not get
changed.
Okay, that's the requirement of the
transaction ID.
And how you add it into your producer
application?
spring.kafka.producer.transaction-id-prefix.
Okay.
So, whatever the name you want to give,
hyphen,
like anything which makes it unique.
Because, let's say, if you See, if you
have only one application, then you can
just simply give like order-serv.
Okay. If you think that this is unique,
then give this. But, if you have
multiple instances, instance one,
instance two, instance three. Okay. So,
you can add this. So, if you're using
Kubernetes, then it will automatically
add a unique host name. And even if you
restart, this host name would be same.
Okay. But, if you have only one
application, you can simply remove it.
You can simply have order-serv-
Okay, and the Spring Boot prefix
automatically append zero something.
So, you have you will have a unique
ID, transaction ID.
Okay. But,
remember that if you have multiple
instances,
then
you should have something that even if
multiple instances are created, each one
should get a different transaction ID.
Okay.
So, here you can use host name. If you
have each instance running at
different port number,
then you can append the port number.
Okay.
Whatever, according to your business on
your application,
you can append something which is
unique. And whenever always make sure
that
you don't do something like random UUID.
You don't append this because if you
restart this application,
you will get new ID.
And that breaks
the
core guarantee of the transaction.
Because, see, transaction can only work
properly
when you have a unique transaction ID.
Unique transaction ID. Even if it
restart, you have the same transaction
ID because it does a lot of mapping
based on this transaction ID also. I
will tell you what all mapping it does.
But, if this transaction ID will get
changed, then whatever the mapping it
stored previously
before the restart, that would get lost.
So, it's the same idempotency problem we
would
come here itself.
Okay.
So, that's the main requirement of
transaction ID.
And this is how in a Spring Boot in
producer application, you can add this.
Order hyphen serve, whatever for
service, you can add serve order hyphen
service hyphen
If you have multiple instances, you can
do this. So, Kubernetes would add the
host name for each instance.
Or you can use server port.
Okay? So, yes.
We will put this in backlog for some
time.
And when we proceed further,
we will get to know about this zombie
fencing.
Because question is definitely this
doubt might have comes to every engineer
that why
why each instance should have a unique
transaction ID. Why why not like one
producer application, no matter how many
instances, why can't we can have just
one
T1 one transaction ID for all?
Okay? We will come to this zombie
fencing, very important part.
So, step one is done that to our
producer application, we have assigned
transaction ID.
Now, the step two is find the
transaction coordinator.
The transaction coordinator is nothing
but the brain of transaction.
This is the one who actually
manage transaction, you can say, in
Kafka, transaction coordinator.
Now, what is transaction coordinator? It
is nothing very very similar to
consumer, you can say that consumer
coordinator, right? In that we have.
Very similar.
Let's say you have three brokers, broker
one, broker two, broker three.
Just one broker
perform this
which perform this manage transaction
also. That broker you can say that known
as transaction coordinator. You can say
that.
But now, let's go one level more deeper
about this.
There is a topic
__ __ transaction __ state. Okay? __ __
two __
transaction __ state.
This is the topic.
Okay, this is the topic name, which is
internally created.
Okay, which is internally created by
Kafka.
And this topic has
50 partitions.
Okay? And this 50 partition is divided
among different brokers.
Okay? Let's say
one partition one to partition 10 hold
by broker one, partition 11 to partition
30 is hold by broker two, partition 31
to partition
50 is hold by broker three. Assume that.
Okay? So, each broker
is the leader of certain partition of
this topic __ __ transaction __ state.
Now,
what our producer application do?
Producer
in the step one, we have assigned the
transaction ID.
So, what it does is and this transaction
ID is unique for the producer. Okay?
So, for this transaction ID, what it
does is it compute hash, hash of
transaction ID
mod 50.
Now, let's say you got 23.
So, this partition 23 of this topic
__ __ transaction __ state.
Okay? So, this topic partition 23
Okay, let's say this is the one,
partition 23. So, broker two
known as the transaction coordinator for
this producer.
Okay? So, for this producer
with transaction ID this one
for which
this partition is computed.
So, no matter what, whatever the
transaction history or metadata
information for this producer is stored
in this partition and this partition is
belongs to this broker. So, this broker
is known as the transaction coordinator.
Very very similar concept to
in the consumer we have uh coordinator,
right? The very very similar top concept
here in the transaction.
So, let's go through this.
So, we have this topic transaction __
state topics hold transaction related
information.
Considered as the brain of transaction.
Okay?
This topic has 50 partition. These
partition are divided among different
brokers, I told you.
Okay? So, very similar. Let's say
partition zero till partition 49. So,
total 50 partition for this topic
and divided among brokers, different
brokers.
So, particular producer transaction goes
to specific partition
topic only. Okay? So, the same concept.
For this producer with transaction,
let's say T1, this producer has
transaction ID T1.
So, when you do hash of T1,
you will get a specific partition.
Okay?
So, for this producer, all the
transaction related information goes
into this partition only.
That's what this line says.
So, for example, producer transaction ID
is order hyphen serve hyphen zero.
So, partition calculation would be hash
of this
topic this transaction ID
mod 50. So, you got partition 23.
So, the leader of partition 23 of topic
is broker two, let's say. Here,
partition 23
leader is broker two, let's say.
So, for this producer, for this
transaction ID, you got partition 23 and
this partition 23 of this topic
the leader is broker two.
So, broker two is considered as the
transaction coordinator for the producer
with transaction ID this one.
Transaction coordinator concept is
clear?
Which like which broker is considered as
the transaction
transaction coordinator? Okay? So, this
can be a transaction coordinator for a
specific producer
whose transaction
or the partition which comes is
among this, managed by this broker.
Similarly, broker two considered as the
transaction coordinator for producer
Okay? Whose transactions goes into
partition which is the leader of
which is the leader
broker two is the leader.
Similarly, broker three can also be a
transaction coordinator
for producers
their transaction for which their
transaction goes into partition
for which broker three is the leader.
I hope concept of transaction
coordinator is clear and also the
transaction is state.
We are going to get one level more
deeper because what data is stored
inside it, that also matters.
So, first understand [snorts] till this.
So, we have a producer.
The first step we did is assigned a
transaction ID to it. Let's say I
assigned this order hyphen serve hyphen
zero. Assume that I have only one
producer. So, that's why I can give like
this. Okay? So, this producer assigned
itself for transaction ID.
Now,
I am doing a step of find the
coordinator. Only once it happens. Okay?
So, what happened is it send the find
coordinator request to any broker, to
any broker.
And it will pass its transaction ID.
Hey, this is my transaction ID.
Find me the transaction coordinator.
Now, what any broker, either B1 or B2 or
B3, out of any broker
get this request, it perform hash of
transaction ID which is sent here mod 50
because there are total 50 partition.
Whatever the partition number came,
this broker will check who is the leader
of this partition of topic __ __ state.
So, let's say it come broker two is the
leader
for this partition of this transaction
state topic.
So, it will say that, "Hey, your
coordinator is broker two."
Okay? So, till here we have covered
step two, find the coordinator. So, I
hope this step is clear.
Now, let's proceed further.
The step three, get the producer ID and
version.
Again, producer ID concept of
idempotency.
Okay? So, why producer ID is required?
You can get more information in
idempotency video also.
But,
when we enable transaction,
transaction also enable idempotency.
Okay? So, we don't have to specifically
say that idempotency equals to true.
If you have enabled that transaction,
idempotency will also get true.
Okay? So, means when idempotency is get
true, you need a PID, producer ID.
Okay? So, our next step is get the
producer ID and version.
So, that's what I have written. When we
use transaction in Kafka, internally it
also enables idempotency and idempotency
need producer ID.
Check this out video idempotency if you
have any doubt. But now let's see this
flow. What happens?
So till now step two flow is clear. So
assume that it all happening in
continuity. Okay? So I'm just going step
by step. So till step till coordinator
have been done. After that what it does,
it do get producer ID. Again, this
happens only once, not again and again.
Okay?
So it says that hey, it send a request.
Now to whom? To the transaction
coordinator.
In the step one it already knows which
broker is my transaction coordinator.
Now it directly send the request
initialize init producer ID request and
it passes transaction ID. Hey, this is
my transaction ID.
Give me the producer ID.
So what transaction coordinator?
The leader of transaction underscore
state topic of partition 23. Because
that's what it got for its transaction
ID.
It got partition 23 and partition 23
leader is broker two. So broker two is
transaction coordinator.
So this is nothing but a broker two, but
this act as a transaction coordinator
for this producer.
Okay?
So it ask the transaction coordinator,
hey, return me the producer ID.
So what transaction coordinator will do?
I told you it manage this topic. So it
write in this topic underscore
underscore transaction underscore state
and this partition 23.
Because this
transaction coordinator is the leader
of this partition.
Okay?
So it write
transaction ID
this
producer ID I am generating let's say
generate five.
Epoch zero state empty partition
involved currently empty. For each one I
will tell you what does it mean. But
first thing understand that the very big
disadvantage of in the idempotency,
you know that when the PID was
generated, nowhere it is stored.
So when the application restart, it
generate a new PID and return to the
producer.
But now here in transaction,
so against a transaction ID,
Okay? So transaction ID is your order
hyphen serve hyphen zero. This is the
transaction ID. Against that it it
stores the PID. Producer ID.
Apart from that it also hold other
information like epoch,
its state, partition involved, which we
will see soon.
So one thing is that in the transaction,
no matter how many times your
application restart, if your application
if your producer has the same
transaction ID, it can always get the
same producer ID.
So the disadvantage in idempotency is
resolved.
Okay?
Now
after writing into this topic particular
partition, it return the
producer. Hey,
you asked for producer ID, right? Here,
this is your producer ID, but epoch is
zero. What is epoch? Consider it as the
version.
So current your version is let's say
zero.
Now understand that whenever a producer
restarts,
okay? So it send this request only once.
Whenever the application is starts or
during its lifetime, it only send this
request once.
So whenever it send this request,
it will pass this transaction ID. For
this transaction ID, it knows that hey,
it already has this PID
five.
But it will every with every request
with every restart it increase the
version. Epoch is considered as a
version.
Initially it was zero, then first
restart happen let's say, then it send
this request again.
So PID five only, but now epoch is one.
And during this PID is five only, but
epoch is two.
It increase the version.
Okay?
And I will tell you why this version is
important. Because this only helps in
avoiding
the zombie fencing.
Initially if you remember,
I told you that every instance of
producer should have different
transaction ID.
Why? Because it helps in avoiding zombie
fencing.
Now we will see what is zombie fencing.
But at this point of time you got to
know that
producer ask the transaction
coordinator, hey, give me the
give me the producer ID.
Transaction coordinator
write this into a partition of this
topic.
Hey, this is the transaction ID. This is
the PID. This is the version. Currently
state is empty. Partition involved is
empty.
And return it.
And I told you I already told you that
in idempotency I have we have covered
this.
So whenever the producer ask for PID
unique ID,
it generate
a PID, but never stored it. So that's
why when you restarted, you get a new
ID. But now this is not with the case.
So it is stored here. Whenever you
restarted, you pass the same transaction
ID. Now against this transaction ID, it
already has the PID.
So the issue is resolved in transaction.
As this topic
now holds the mapping.
Okay? So this is the all the information
is stored.
Transaction ID,
you have a PID producer ID, epoch, which
is act as a version,
state, partition involved and timeout.
So PID is the unique producer ID.
Epoch considered at already told you
considered as a version. 0 1 2 3
likewise.
State. So see, in transaction, states
flow like this in Kafka. Earlier it is
empty.
When the transaction is start, it is now
ongoing.
When after it is about to commit, first
it goes into prepare commit and from
prepare commit it goes to the committed
state. So these are all states.
Similarly from ongoing if abort is going
to happen, first prepare to abort and
then it goes to abort.
So these two steps are critical because
after this step there is no kind of a
step back.
If
prepare to commit or prepare to abort
happens, then no matter what, whether
anything down or up, ultimately
transaction has to be commit.
If prepare abort has been written into
the state, no matter what,
if it if any broker is down or anything
up, whenever the network is up, it has
to complete and do the abort. That's the
same rule into the transaction. And
maybe if you're working with DBMS, the
same thing.
Once this is written prepare to commit,
prepare to abort, after that it has to
commit.
Okay? It has to be aborted. If you have
a two phase commit if you remember that
one. So this is the flow. The very
similar flow here itself.
Then partitions involved. So in what
this happen is
in an ongoing transaction,
what all partitions are getting touched,
it is stored. Let's say for topic A
partition zero is touched. Topic B
partition two is touched. So
whichever
partitions of us different different
topics, okay? Which are part or which
are need to be grouped together in this
transaction, those are returned
partitions involved.
Let's say topic A partition two,
topic B partition one. These two
involved in this specific partition.
Which currently the state is this.
And the timeout. Maximum time this
transaction can remain in ongoing state.
After that this transaction coordinate
will abort it. So see,
you your transaction cannot be always
like in open. When I say open, consider
that ongoing. Okay? Open or ongoing.
So once you start the transaction, let's
say it is in ongoing state or open
state.
But it cannot be always in open state,
right? So there is some maximum timeout
limit we have to set. Hey, if
transaction is not prepared to commit,
move to the next
state
commit or abort
within this much maximum time, then go
and abort it itself. So this is the
maximum timeout your transaction
coordinator will wait for your
transaction to complete.
Okay?
So these all things are stored into this
topic transaction underscore state
topic.
Now advantage of keeping information
like this. First advantage I've already
told you, it solves the problem of the
idempotency.
Even if your producer application
restart,
it sends the transaction ID.
Okay? It send this request
initialize producer ID request, pass the
transaction ID.
From this transaction ID, it will see
that okay, there is already a record
present
and it just find out the same PID.
And it return the same PID.
Okay? So
the problem with idempotency is
resolved. First thing.
Second is it helps in zombie fencing.
Very important again initially we have
kept it like we will see it later. Now,
let's see it.
Now, understand that.
What is zombie fencing? Let's say you
have a producer one.
It give itself transaction ID.
Okay? And it send the hey, give me the
producer ID request.
And it got that hey, this is the
producer ID. Epoch is zero currently all
empty something written and it return.
Producer ID is five, epoch is zero.
And it start the transaction, let's say.
It start the trans- transaction and it
is touching multiple topics partitions.
So,
let's say it has some record.
Producer ID is five.
Epoch is zero.
State is ongoing. These are all the
partition it is touching.
Let have So, don't worry about this what
all happening.
Understand
the intention.
So, producer one has started the
transaction. So, it is ongoing.
But after because of some network issue,
there is some pause happen. Network
pause happen.
So, maybe if you are using Kubernetes,
it
auto span new
pod with the same transaction ID, let's
say.
So, now you got a producer ID
but with the same transaction ID T1.
So, what it will do is it will send this
request.
Okay? It will send this request. So,
currently you have this row present.
Okay, PID five epoch zero. So, when the
new request come,
what transaction coordinator will say
that, hey, there is already a mapping
present for this T1.
Okay? So, what it will do is
first, it will whatever the ongoing, it
will abort it.
It will abort it.
Okay? After that, it will increase the
epoch version.
Okay? It will increase the epoch
version. Now, it become one.
Okay? And then it will reset everything.
The state is now empty.
Partition involved empty. Whatever the
timeout default, it will set it.
Okay?
And it will return.
Producer ID is five.
But now the version is one.
Because this is a
new producer but the same transaction ID
pass. So, every time this PID call
request comes, it just increase the
epoch version.
Because the T1 is already exist, it just
increase the epoch version.
And with the previous epoch previous
version, if there is anything about if
anything is ongoing open, it will abort
it first.
So, that happened. But now, let's say
somehow this old producer one
get revived.
Now, earlier for it,
everything was like ongoing. Now, it
let's say want to commit. Hey, commit.
I am
So, this is my transaction ID.
My producer ID was five and version is
zero.
So, now it will check transaction
coordinator that okay, this transaction
ID okay, producer ID five okay.
Version epoch is zero. Hey, but
currently I have one.
Means this is zombie.
Means
previously it marked as considered this
producer might be inactive. So, new
producer has taken its place. But
somehow this old producer is coming
back.
So, it fence it. It throws producer
fence exception.
Okay?
Because when the new
init producer ID request come, it
already whatever it's ongoing was it
already aborted it. It
make everything set reset again and
state empty, partition empty, increase
the version. Okay? Everything.
Now, if come with the old epoch,
so it considered as a zombie. So, now it
will fence it. It will stop it. Hey,
you are old.
Okay?
For me, you do not exist. For me, I will
only entertain
PID with epoch one now.
You got it zombie fencing?
So,
advantage of storing information like
this
epoch, right? It also helps in zombie
fencing. Many time what happened is old
producer somehow come back, send the
request. So, those will not get passed
through.
This is clear till now?
So,
we going to do a step four. So, a step
one transaction ID.
Transaction coordinator
also has been fetched.
Then it got producer ID and version.
This all this is all producer able to
do.
Now,
a step four begin transaction and it
start sending the event.
So, it has to begin the transaction.
Okay?
Now, once the transaction is begun,
what it will do is it will send, let's
say order event.
This is the key. This is the order. Like
normal
event it send.
So, now you can say that there is an
interceptor.
Okay? Before it do an actual send
to a particular partition leader
for this order topic,
it first send the request to the
transaction coordinator.
Hey, transaction coordinator.
I am going to send
in this topic.
And it knows which partition also.
In this partition.
Okay?
It will send this.
Transaction ID it will pass. Hey, this
is my transaction ID. This is the
process producer ID. My version is this.
And this is the partition
of an order event I'm going to touch.
What transaction coordinator will do? It
will update.
It already has transaction [snorts]
ID.
It will check okay, producer ID five.
This request is coming for version epoch
zero. I also have epoch zero. So, yes,
let me pass through. So, it will update
the state from empty to ongoing.
Partition involved update empty to order
event P2.
Okay? This is going to touch.
So, it will send okay and then
ultimately the send call will go to a
particular broker, let's say.
So, this is the broker, let's say leader
of
this topic partition two order event
partition two.
So, that it will write its log. Simple
log.
Okay?
It will acknowledge.
Now, let's say
this producer is sending another
transaction payment event.
Very similar to how it send an event.
Again, it will call would be
intercepted. First, it will tell to the
transaction coordinator.
Hey, my transaction ID is this.
My producer ID and version is this. I am
going to touch payment event partition
one.
So, it will update. Hey, okay,
transaction ID
producer ID is five. Version is zero.
Yes, match. Okay.
Status is still ongoing. Partition you
are touching is payment event P1. So, it
will update the partition involved.
It will send okay and then the send
request to the partition leader
of payment events partition one. Let's
say broker two is the leader of
partition one of payment event.
So, it will simply write it log.
And it will send the acknowledge.
So, this flow is clear. Begin
transaction and send events. So, we have
begin the transaction and events
start sending the events. So, every send
before that it got intercepted, you can
see. And update
on transaction state topic happen.
Now, you can say that of two phase
protocol is started.
Because now after you have completed all
the send,
now only two things you have to do.
Whether you have to commit or whether
you have to abort.
Okay? So, this prepare commit prepare
abort, you can say that internal. Why is
that? I will show tell you also.
But for us,
two phase protocol start because after
this now we want to go to the commit or
abort. So, let's see commit.
So, now what would happen?
Let's say all the send event done.
Now, commit transaction phase.
What it will do is it will send to the
transaction coordinator that I want to
do commit.
This is my transaction ID. This is the
producer ID and this is the version. I
want to commit now.
So, first thing first is that this
transaction coordinator is stored as a
prepare commit before it goes to the
broker. Because this is point of no
return.
Once this prepare commit is written,
after that no matter if this broker down
the order event or the partition event
this broker down or whatever even if
this transaction coordinator down, no
matter what,
whenever they will get up, they will
start from here itself. So, it has to be
commit only.
It cannot goes to the ongoing state now
or it cannot goes to the abort.
You have written a prepare commit. Hey,
I got a commit request. I have written
prepare commit first.
Okay?
It hasn't goes to the broker one broker
two yet. It has written prepare commit
first. Okay?
And after this once it is written, then
there is no point of return. Ultimately,
this state will change to commit only.
And how this change will list to commit?
So, now it will send to the broker one.
Hey.
This is a commit for this producer ID
and epoch zero.
So, it add a control record commit.
Okay?
Now, very interesting thing.
If you go the check send event, okay?
You know that during the send event, the
transaction coordinator write into this
transaction state topic
that this is an ongoing the partition
involved is this.
And after that it done, it send to the
partition leader and log has written.
Now, in this log in header,
it add few more information. What
information? It has PID.
It has epoch.
And also has like is transactional.
True.
This three information also it append.
Okay? And after that it has a record.
If it is a batch, multiple records like
this.
But the header has PID and epoch and
also is transaction equals to true.
So, the same thing.
Now,
this transaction coordinator first send
the commit
control
control command you can say commit
control command to the broker one.
This partition two.
Hey, for this producer ID and this
epoch,
record this.
And it will add one log simply.
Remember that
the logs
or the rights
in Kafka is append only. It cannot
update, delete anything. So, this just
add new record into its log file that
hey, okay.
PID five, epoch zero,
control record is true. This is control
record and commit.
That's all. It just append one log.
And it say done.
After that, it send
to the
It will check its partition involved. It
will pass to the another partition,
payment event partition one.
It will send it. Hey,
record a
control record commit for this PID and
epoch zero. It will also do that, okay?
PID five,
epoch zero,
control. This is a control record true.
And I want to commit. So, this will just
append into its log file. It will say
done.
Now, from all the partition which are
involved, it get a done. Ultimately, it
finalize and change to commit.
Commit completed.
Done.
And it will return success.
Done. Commit totally done.
Okay?
And very very similar abort. No
difference.
If you understand the commit, the same
thing. Well, if now let's see if it has
to abort,
again, it will first do prepare hyphen
abort. After that, no point, no return.
Okay? No matter if any broker down,
transaction coordinator down. Whenever
it will be up,
ultimately, this would be
changed to abort only. And how it will
be changed to abort? It will send the
abort control
to each of this partition. And once they
write one record,
whatever the producer ID, epoch, control
is true, control record and abort.
They will send done. After that, it will
say abort completed. Success.
Okay? So, prepare abort phase is very
very similar to commit only.
And after that,
from a step four, the process begins.
Okay?
Then after that, new transaction, new
transaction. Remember that
transaction
in producer is single
threaded.
When one transaction is going on,
okay?
Let's say for this transaction ID
T1.
For this transaction ID for producer,
producer
with transaction ID T1,
if this is ongoing,
you cannot
start another transaction.
Okay? You cannot restart another
transaction. So, it's a single threaded.
One transaction at a time happens.
Okay? So, now one transaction is
completed.
Now,
from a step four, begin transaction, the
new transaction get started. So, step
four is this one. So, begin transaction
next time,
it will before it send,
it will make it everything like
transaction ID, whatever the PID, epoch,
state ongoing, whatever the partition it
touching, it will update it. It will now
restart
everything.
So, got it?
I will show you the demo. Things will
get clear. So, we will see this
implementation first because now we will
be able to club all the things together.
And after that, we will see the demo and
that will get make things super clear.
Okay? And still,
till now what we have seen is the
producer side, producer side
transaction.
How consumer consume this records, we
have to see that.
So, first again, this is all producer
side changes I am showing you.
In the application.properties, we have
to put a transaction ID prefix order
hyphen serve hyphen. I have only one
producer, that's why I haven't put
anything.
Okay? So, this would be my unique
transaction ID. So,
Spring Boot will append
zero after it.
Okay? So, this is my transaction ID.
And the timeout by default is 60 second
even if you don't write it. But if you
want to change it,
you can add this transaction timeout
millisecond. You know what uh where it
will get updated?
This one.
In the transaction state, it has
multiple fields. So, this timeout,
okay? After this timeout, even if you
have any transaction ongoing, this will
get aborted.
Okay?
But this configuration
if you want default itself, let you need
only one. Otherwise, if you want to
change it, you can use it.
Second thing is it just a controller
method. I have added a API transaction
hyphen commit. It just invoke the
send this service layer.
Okay? All I have is now order event and
payment
payment object you can say that payment
object, order object. Whatever the order
object I got, I created one payment
object and I just called my service
layer.
Now, this is important.
Okay? Now, in this,
this is very similar to how producer
used to
send a
event. dot send
the topic,
the key,
and the
object. Okay? Now, only difference is
we have to wrap it inside begin
transaction,
then your code logic,
then once successful commit.
If there is any failure, abort.
So, that's why now
Kafka template.send.
Now, I did Kafka template execute in
transaction. We have to use it execute
in transaction. So, if you go inside
this method execute in transaction,
okay? You would see this.
It will begin the transaction.
Okay?
Then do in operation
like your logic.
Like this logic.
Okay? This is the lambda expression,
right? So, this will get invoked.
This lambda expression. So, all the
events which has to be grouped together.
So, order events, payment events,
all this. So, that will run. Send
order event.
Send
payment event. Okay?
After that, everything is success,
commit the transaction.
If
try catch, anything failure, abort
transaction.
So, this is you can say that if you want
to write it, you can write it also. But
there is already a method present Kafka
template
execute in transaction.
Okay? And it's a functional interface,
we can
provide this lambda expression.
This lambda expression is nothing.
You can just simply like how you how we
used to provide send the events, we can
add as many events
we want to publish. Okay? And that will
just get invoked here
between begin and commit.
And but if there is any exception comes
during this send,
abort will happen.
But very important thing which many
ignores is that with each send,
we have to do join.
If you remember
the from the producer,
this diagram, if you remember, I told
you that application thread is only work
till record accumulator. After that, it
get free.
Okay?
It
It fulfill It You can say that
uh
It is free to serve more request. After
that,
there is a different thread, sender
thread, which works.
But in case of transaction,
we want to wait. Hey, I want to send
whether any failure comes or not. If any
failure comes, we have to abort it.
Okay? That's why I put join. When you do
don't join, it will wait. So, your
application thread waits here.
Okay? The standard thread will pick it
up and whatever the response will come
acknowledge proper.
Okay? If it is come proper acknowledge
this properly paid, no issues,
everything fine,
then only it will proceed further. But
if any exception come during send, let's
say,
okay? Uh
So, what would happen generally is that
your broker will book it will up end
into the log and it will send. Okay?
Then ultimately it will get acknowledged
done.
If But if there is any issue at the
broker layer while inserting into the
log everywhere,
it will fail it here itself and
ultimately it exception about will be
called. So, remember when you're doing a
transaction, with every send, we have to
make use of join.
If you don't make use of join, what
would happen is your thread become free
here itself.
Okay? Now, what happened is
if later once your transaction get
completed,
then you got that hey, it is fail.
Completable future, remember? In the
producer it's a completable future. Now
you say that okay, it is fail. But you
won't be able to do about after then.
So, that's why with every send, we have
to wait for the broker response.
If they're able to write it properly,
then only we proceed to the next send.
And when every send is proper,
then only we do commit. Otherwise, if
there is any issue with any send, this
join itself will fail and we will abort
it.
Okay?
So, let's
see a demo.
So, first thing I am doing is so
we have already done this setup a lot.
Okay? So, I'm just uh starting con- uh
controller one,
controller two.
So, both controllers are starting
and I have three brokers. I'm starting
the broker one.
Okay, sorry. Uh just a sec.
Broker level, no. Broker one I'm
starting.
Then I'm starting broker two.
I'm starting broker three. So, two
controller, three brokers are started.
Okay? And uh
Let's see.
The same thing I have is in
application.properties,
I have added this. Transaction ID prefix
order-serve.
Zero would be appended by or some number
would be appended by Spring.
Okay? I think it's always zero. First uh
one producer application, it always
append zero.
And the timeout. If it is not required,
if you have to change it, you can change
it, but this is the default itself.
Okay? So, only you need transaction ID
prefix.
Then in order controller, I have this
transaction commit endpoint.
I just created an object of payment, the
same thing.
Calling the service.
In service layer, I have execute in
transaction. If you go inside this, the
same thing I showed you that begin.
Okay? Then after that, it invokes
over this lambda.
This lambda.
Okay?
And if all success, it will do commit.
If there is any exception, it will abort
it. Okay?
And our lambda is simple. I am doing
publishing an event, very simple. Dot
send similarly,
but also doing join.
This is the system.out.println to like
which partition it goes.
Similarly, I'm sending
touching payments events.
This is just a system.out.println.
That's all.
So, let's hit it.
Transaction
commit.
And let's see that currently at the Let
me start the producer itself. So, first
also see
Also, let's see that
currently order event do not exist.
Similarly,
payment events
>> [snorts]
>> do not exist. So, when we will start the
producer application,
so during the start itself, we will
create this.
Create order, create payment. So, let me
start the producer application.
So, I've started the producer
application now. Now, let's see this
first order events.
Okay?
So, three partitions. Which all
applications are the leader? Which all
brokers are the leader? It's there.
Similarly, payment events also is there
now.
Cool.
Now, let's
hit this endpoint.
With order
one.
Committed.
Let me see.
Order is written into partition zero,
offset zero.
So, partition zero. Who is the leader of
partition zero? Order.
Leader five.
Leader five is let's say one is
controller one, two is controller two,
three is broker one,
uh four is broker two, five is broker
three. So, we have to check the broker
three logs.
Okay? So, let me check the broker three
logs.
So, there would be huh.
So, we have to check the broker three
logs.
Order-
partition zero, right?
Partition zero.
Okay. So, now here notice that.
So,
here if you see,
so this is the record which goes, right?
O-1.
This is what we have inserted.
But here if you see first header is that
transaction equals to true.
Okay?
Transaction is true. And after that, it
has producer ID,
P ID, and epoch zero.
If you remember, if you just recall it
from our flow,
okay?
The first thing it has done is
when it added into the log,
it added P ID, epoch, and is transaction
true.
Okay? Added into the header.
And then our record.
At offset zero, it added our record.
Okay? After that,
it goes into the pay- payments. So, in
the payment, we have to see now
payment is written into partition two.
So, payment is written into partition
two. Partition two leader is five.
Again, the broker three. Payment events,
right?
Okay? So, we have to now check
broker three only.
Payment events,
but partition two.
Okay?
So, here if you see
that
producer ID,
epoch, transaction equals to true. Okay?
And this is the data.
Pay-
the order ID zero minus one. Okay? Now,
after that,
everything is done properly. So, if you
see our code,
it has written into order ID, it has
written into payment. After that,
the transaction will properly do a
commit commit transaction. So, now
if you recall, when it commit, what
happened is
it will send
to each broker that add a control
record. So, now we will see that in the
here, order event one,
if you see at offset one,
what you see? Producer ID is zero, epoch
is zero.
Is transaction is true? Is control true?
Means whatever the record you are going
to see is the control record. Okay? And
what is the control record is? Commit.
Similarly, payment events, if you see
offset one,
producer ID zero, epoch zero,
transaction true, control. This is a
control record. What is the
commit.
Okay?
Similarly, here I have one more endpoint
abort. Now, in this what I'm doing is
the same thing. First, it will put into
order event and after that I'm throwing
a run time exception.
Okay? Just to show that it has been
aborted properly. So,
abort.
O-2.
Aborted. Transaction will abort. So, now
let's see this uh let me first see.
Okay? Order sent to partition two. Order
goes to the partition two. So, let me
see which is the leader.
Order event.
Partition two, leader four. Leader four
means your broker two.
So, I need to check the broker two logs.
So, let me clear it first.
So, I need to check the broker two log.
And which partition it goes? P2.
Okay, not payment events.
It's order hyphen events.
Okay. Now here if you see
first is transactional. So O hyphen two,
right? So here if you see
producer ID zero, epoch zero,
transactional is true. This is not a
control record. And here if you see the
order O2.
But after that I send an exception. So
this should be rolled back, aborted.
Okay. So that should add a new record
offset one, right? So here producer ID
zero, epoch zero
transactional true, is control true.
This is a control record. What is it?
Abort.
Okay. And also if you just see
__transaction__
state
you'll find that that there are total 50
partitions, zero to 49.
Okay. Each having three replicas.
So you got it?
This is at producer layer. So in
producer how transaction is managed. Now
the another problem or you can say that
another challenge come is that how
consumer understand this records. Okay.
So now we have seen this one.
In the order even log you see that first
producer ID
epoch ID, transactional is true, and
then you will see the record.
Similarly
uh when the commit happen
you will see that is control is true and
the commit.
And the payment even logs the similarly.
Now the thing is that how consumer
consume this records.
That I will show you in the next part.
But I hope
how transaction is handled at the
producer side
that is clear.
Okay.
Let's see you in the next part. How
consumer handles it. Very interesting.